[Music]
good evening and good day everybody
Welcome to the ask abijit Show episode
228 I hope everybody is doing
fantastic uh and let me see who all is
there on the live chat before I begin
with the Q&A I can see uh Mr
8ers Abhijit chavda light uh J prit
Singh crazy brain abishek barot Sami Jan
two idiot nris Ashish pandel T tanay
Chandra pratik Kish achara Chri Dr Atul
Raja Akash Kumar snea Anita Raji gon
dungar Singh Chan dearon bachara Ashish
pandel uh vickram geopolitical Adel
coder from South Africa Gana Joi gorov
jot Mami Peter Estrada from Australia
Nan sahai Global citizen pray Paul from
Kolkata crazy brain Barat first feminist
Slayer ragir sanki B goami geopolitical
dub Astra tab Krishna ragunath from the
sues Netherlands pulkit Grover bries
SK KL parik but prar Gupta tensi Dr Atul
Tushar nagar prabhunath strike 47 thus B
akar rooni
sarar Kush Abu drawing in art kushu
drawing in art Lost Child pin Kumar Raji
mavin
SES ER Paradox
debarun Pampa Barman Ashish yoga nanit
and lots and lots of other people I
won't be able to greet you all but thank
you so much for being on this live
stream so I have as always received a
whole lot of questions in the comments
let me greet some more of you shaah
abishek mahita busti aush rextro Matthew
Jacob and everybody else all right all
right so as always I've got a bunch of
questions a lot of questions uh that you
have asked in the comments and I'm going
to take as many of these as possible and
later on after that if possible I'll
take some questions from the live chat
as well so let's get going with the
questions what questions do we
have okay the first question is about
the Los Angeles fires dungar sing Chan
says what are your thoughts on the LA
fires vicam geopolitical says the US is
the most technologically advanced
country and the richest as well it might
have all the necessary things required
to control or stop the wildfires why is
it unable to do anything despite being
capable of doing something uh
so um look I haven't really I haven't
really looked into the causes of the
wildfires and why they spread but it's
clear that look this is not some
forested area this is uh Los Angeles one
of the biggest cities in the US uh and
the US is the world's most powerful most
technologically mostly most
technologically advanced nation and they
should be able to to ensure that a
catastroph of this this uh magnitude
doesn't happen now we have to first of
all understand that fires happen because
of many causes there could be artificial
causes like arson some people have
criminal Tendencies and they like to set
fires that's one possibility okay
another possibility is that wildfires
can can you know grow out of uh can run
out of control and uh encroach upon uh
inhabited areas and wildfires are really
difficult to control it's it's not as
easy as it sounds wildfires can be
really difficult to control I I remember
uh in 1988 there was this massive
wildfire in Yellowstone National Park in
the
US and it started off as small wildfires
but it ran out of control it it uh I
think
it burnt up a third or a quarter or
something of the entire National Park to
some you know yeah that sort of thing
happened that's 1988 and they were not
able to control this Wildfire at all
eventually they were able to stop it but
not before it caused tremendous damage
to the national park that's 8
and I visited Yellowstone in what 2002
or something about yes around that time
and you could still see the effects of
the devastation so it's not like they
didn't want to stop it they could not
stop it and they did a tremendous amount
of damage now when it comes to more
recent incidents you had that uh
devastating fire in Hawaii right that
also was
strange and there have been allegations
put out in the US media in the US Not By
Us by by the Americans themselves that
it was set on purpose and the rich
people wanted that land which is like a
prime real estate location but it was um
but but the land was owned by local
localites who did not want to give it up
and that sort of thing so maybe that's
why they set set it on fire on purpose
that's the kind of claim some people
have made in the US when it comes to
this fire in Los Angeles once again I'm
not sure what the deal is apparently a
lot of the people who lost their homes
were uninsured their insurance was
cancelled recently which is kind of
strange and
fishy but look it could be an accident
it could be something that the the
authorities could do nothing about or
maybe there could have been something
behind it we don't know for sure we
don't know I cannot speculate but what I
can tell you is that if something like
this happened in some somewhere
somewhere in India and the entire Global
media would have come together to to
make fun of India and to accuse India of
you know not doing enough for its
citizens and all that but if it happens
in the US it's all hush hush so that's
the kind of double standards you you
witness uh in the media among the
netizens on social media and and so on
if it happens in the west if it happens
in the US nobody will will raise any
questions if something similar happens
in India my goodness everybody's going
to point fingers I remember we talking
about um I think somewhere early in in
the first half of the
2000s uh
there was this big flood in
Mumbai okay it was I think 26th of July
to 2004 2005 one of those two I think
2004 and I happened to be caught in that
flood okay it was a gigantic down
downpour of rain it was like buckets of
rain were being appended on your head uh
on a continuous basis the heaviest
rainfall ever recorded anywhere in the
world in in a 24-hour period and Mumbai
was devastated and I had a fight for the
US that day and I had to obviously that
flight nobody because the airport was
down under
underwater so a week later everything
goes back to kind of it starts going
back to normal and I take the next a
week a week later I take a flight to the
US and I go and I was working as a cyber
coie essentially you know that term so
uh I was working for an American company
in the it sector back in the day and
there was this elderly guy or there
American guy white man who was who would
come to me during lunch break every day
and tell me the situation in Mumbai is
dire and there's this possibility of an
outbreak of Cera and seven I don't know
seven people have died and so much
damage to infrastructure these many
million dollars and all that every day
he would come and taunt me like that and
then Hurricane Katrina
happened okay Louisiana New Orleans New
Orleans was abandoned by the US
government and then that gentleman just
evaporated Into Thin Hair I could not
find him again so that's the kind of
double stand standards that people have
India did a tremendous job when that
Mumbai uh flood
happened and it was much it was a much
better job than what the Americans did
with Hurricane
Katrina so you know that's the kind of
double standards we have so but that's
the deal but uh I of course cannot
speculate about what really happened and
what really caused the LA fires Los
Angeles fires and why were why did did
it cause so much damage I don't know
eventually hope y an investigation May
reveal the
truth okay skip dis
check says uh if you were given a chance
by the government of India to guide them
okay or give them the very best
objectives that may be more realistic or
of getting accomplished in the next five
years in the current geopolitical
scenario also considering the political
pressures and challenges they face both
internally and externally What would
that advice
be well first of all I am nobody to uh
advise the government of India they are
very wise people and we have very wise
leader the Prime Minister and so on but
if I had to let's say give some kind of
uh guidance and give them some
objectives that that what are what what
what are the priorities the nation
should have the next five years let's
say uh given the current geopolitical
climate what would I say look the
problems we Face from the Indian
perspective are internal as well as
external and if you want to be strong
externally geopolitically you have to
strengthen yourself internally as well
so first of all what India needs to have
it is high time we need to have this is
a war on
corruption corruption is a major Bane
for India it is what what destroys
India's potential and it is something
that has permeated every level of
governance in this country EX except for
hopefully most likely the very top right
but everywhere else you have corruption
everywhere the whole system runs on
corruption there needs to be a war on
corruption it will save so much of
India's hard earned money it will it
will ease everything up it it wastes so
much of India's potential we need to
have a war of War on corruption and that
will automatically give you much better
ease of doing business okay that's
number one that's an inter thing
secondly once again internal I would say
India needs to end reservations and end
this culture of giving freebies to
people to all random people based on
what sort of vote bank they
represent that's another thing that that
really hampers India's potential hampers
India's growth and and destroys India's
potential
reservations the lack of Merit and this
culture of giving freebies this yoga and
that yoga and this LLY yoga and that LLY
yoga waste of India's taxpayer resources
okay that's number two what would I say
number three India needs to focus on
economic growth economic growth which
means we need to become a manufacturing
power a major manufacturing power and we
need to focus on exports I don't care
what we manufacture manufacture
everything manufacture pins manufacture
cups manufacture ball bearings
manufacture everything from top to
bottom from the lowest level of
complexity to the highest level of
complexity manufacturing needs to happen
India needs to become a manufacturing
power and it will happen only if we end
this if we have a war on corruption we
end corruption and have better much
better ease of doing
business next we need to continue uh
growing our you know ramping up our
infrastructure you know roads Railways
airports Bridges whatever we we are
infrastructure poor much of our our
infastructure is Antiquated and
crumbling we need to seriously seriously
build infrastructure and that will
generate a tremendous amount of
employment as well it will help the
economy as well so infrastructure is
something we need to keep focusing on
when it comes to education it's a
long-term problem India's education
system is garbage it's rotten and the
so-called new education policy does
nothing to address the real core issues
the fundamental defects in the education
system okay it's like putting lipstick
on a pig that's what they've done but
yeah I mean reforming the education
system will take at least a couple of
decades so what would I say we need to
do in the next five years one very
simple thing we can do immediate Ely is
that the government should decree that
degrees are
optional make degrees optional and allow
companies to hire based purely on your
skills you may or may not have a degree
you may not have a college degree you
may not have a 10 standard degree
doesn't matter if you have the skills
then you should be hired so you should
be allowed to hire whether or not a
candidate has a degree or not just based
on their
skills so that's something the
government can do right now but yeah it
would kind of destroy the education
sector I mean the people leech off the
education sector there's a tremendous
amount of corruption as there as well
but that's something that can happen and
that would really really uh you know
give Wings to a lot of
people uh next we need to go all in on
high technology semiconductors robotics
drones artificial intelligence machine
learning all of that and it's not enough
to adopt to have the greatest amount of
adoption in the world of these
Technologies we don't want to adopt what
others are doing we want to lead
we have leaders who who extol the fact
that we are among the high the the
largest adopters of artificial
intelligence but who are the guys who
are dishing out the AI systems it's not
us so we need to become leaders it's not
enough to merely adopt we need to
lead then we need ATA indigenous
indigenization of the arms industry very
important very important then obviously
we need to focus on jet engines and
fighter aircraft we we already spoke
about drones drones are a great
defensive measure and limited offensive
measure as well you know shallow depth
offensive measure tremendous you can
overwhelm an enemy with draws uh but we
also need to focus on jet engines we
need to anyhow acquire a high quality
jet engine buy Big B steel I don't care
and we need to have our own fighter
aircraft of various kinds so that there
is that then space exploration we need
to double down on space exploration ISO
needs to be given much more funding and
the leway to to undertake uh ambitious
projects not incremental small little
changes real ambitious projects that's
what isra needs to do I mean why do we
we trying to develop a rocket that is
twice as powerful as the previous one
why not develop a rocket that's 20 times
more powerful we have the ability to do
that but no we don't have the
ambition I'm sure the scientists and
engineers at ISRO have the ambition but
it's the political leaders who don't
have it uh so we need to focus on space
exploration we need to focus on building
capabilities at scale at scale so once
we demonstrate a certain capability we
need to start executing and using it at
scale not once in seven years okay we
went to Mars in in the in 2000 whatever
now we will wait 20 years to go back to
Mars no send one spacecraft to Mars
every year and a better spacecraft every
year of course it cost money but it's
not a whole lot of
money and why can't we have an Indian
start Starling H why do we need a
foreign Starling to beam the to beam the
internet into India why can't we have
our own constellation our own Starling
so we need to be ambitious I don't see
the ambition in the Indian political
class the leadership
unfortunately and lastly I would say
that U the West we know now we're
talking geopolitics pure geopolitics the
West uses religion as a geopolitical
tool of interfering in our country we
need to end that we need to ban
that and the government has been very
defensive about this we're doing nothing
essentially about this you know the West
uses religion as a geopolitical tour and
Wasing its effects everywhere that needs
to end so these are the things I would
say India needs to focus on obviously
it's very easy to give out a list and
say that do this it's much more
difficult to execute Implement all this
but yes that's why leader leaders exist
that's why we vote them to power and we
give them the resources of the entire
country get this done so this is what I
would say India needs to do and India's
leadership needs to do in the next five
years four and a half years half an year
half a year is gone roughly so
yeah so good question by slip dis
check vicam geopolitical says ISRO has
successfully completed the docking
Mission what are My Views I think it's
great fantastic it's extremely
complicated a docking Mission it's like
you
take you have let's say you have bottle
with a lid right it's it's it's
apparently very simple superficially
from a from a certain perspective you
take the bottle and you screw screw the
lid on that's it but imagine doing that
in space two satellites they have to
dock precisely and and and the the the
the two satellites need to come together
and the Locking mechanisms mechanism
needs to lock in place it's extremely
complicated when you're out there in
orbit in Earth orbit traveling at I
don't know what
that at orbital speed around the
planet so that's extremely complicated
it's a very delicate operation the my
minute test of mistakes can destroy both
the
spacecraft and I think only three other
nations have the ability to do this the
US the USSR which is Russia now and the
Chinese have done that and now we have
done it so we have demonstrated that we
have the ability to make satellites dock
in space which would be extremely useful
when we have a space station say in 10
years time so we have a space station
out there and we sending a bunch of
astronauts to to the space station we're
going to send them in in a capsule a
Space Capsule a small spacecraft which
will then have to dock with the aircraft
with the space
station so unless you are able to do you
cannot send the astronauts in there and
and whatever right so that sort of thing
so it's very important we do this so now
that we have achieved this we need to
practice it over and over again it's not
enough to demonstrate it once and then
wait for the next 10 years before you do
do it again we need to do it over and
over
again so I'm glad we have done this it's
it tells you it the engineers at ISRO
demonstrate over and over again they can
do things that the only the best in the
world can do so why not give them more
ambitious challenges more ambitious uh
projects to work on so I'm very glad we
have done this I would like to
congratulate
ISRO uh the nation obviously is very
proud of them but we need to empower
them they can do much more they can do
way much way more way more if if just
given the
resources and they go ahead that okay
take this money and do something really
ambitious do something others very few
can do or maybe nobody has done before
that sort of
challenge okay Vikram geopolitical has
two questions what effect will the 2025
bakum have on India's soft power how
does the world look at this Festival the
BBC described the mahak as naked Ash
smeared athetics to lead India bathing
spectacle but clo but calls but the BBC
calls in England's nudist Festival the
biggest natural natur naturist Festival
how come some some traditions are seen
as Natural Way others are judged
differently what are your thoughts on
this okay let me take the second
question first what are my thoughts on
what the BBC has said well they are
simply doing what they've always been
doing super racist super Hindu phobic
and they hate India and the BBC is this
old Antiquated colonial era organism U
Legacy Media organization of the British
Empire and they have the good old
British Raj era attitudes towards India
and they they obviously are extremely
jealous of the fact that India has gone
way past the UK in terms of geopolitical
relevance and hard
power so uh they they are very jealous
and they they they are very recent full
of
India and the Hindu phobia uh obviously
is has always has always been uh a
component of their India
coverage um and they will often use
Indian origin people to Pedal this Hindu
phobia and you know the
BBC you know what's been happening in
the UK right it's all around it's it's
now finally after several decades become
big news the
Scandal I don't know how many thousands
of of of of little English girls were
exploited by by Pakistani rape
gangs it was going on for decades and
what did the BBC do about that everyone
knew about this they kept mum and these
Shameless people who should never be
allowed to show their face in public or
or to put out an article again the they
have the
tarity to uh pedal the hinduphobia
against
us these people should be ashamed of
themselves not just the BBC the entire
nation of the UK should be ashamed of
itself absolute set of
losers so that's all I have to say about
the BBC and the UK overall a bunch of
losers they have no right to criticize
anybody for anything for the next one
th000 years Shameless people can't take
care of your take care of your own
daughters and you're going to judge
others Shameless
people um so yeah that's that's my
response to the second question what
effect will the 2025 mahak have on India
soft power
none uh see why will it have no effect
on India soft power it's because
Hinduism isn't cool it's not even cool
in India I mean if you see the comments
you see on Indian social media about the
mahak half of them are are negative
hinduphobic Indians are ashamed of their
own culture and traditions Indians are
tremendously deracinated and nobody sees
Hinduism is
cool unless a culture is seen as cool
it's going to have no positive effect on
your software maybe it will have a
negative effect on your soft power but
it doesn't mean we give up our
culture so I don't see the mahak has as
as being something relevant on a global
geopolitical stage I don't see I don't
see it as a something that will
positively affect impact India soft
power the most the majority of the world
doesn't
care and who whoever is noticing this
they will see it as a very strange
representation of a strange Pagan uh
non-abrahamic
culture and they don't get it and they
don't care and most of them will look at
it negatively so that's just the way it
is how should we
care how do we care what people think
how do we care what the world thinks
about us we we are 1.4 billi of us right
how do we care so just
just practice your culture that's
it okay PR Paul says how do you
interpret the recent phone call between
Trump and Xi Jinping where they
discussed trade fentel Tick Tock and
Global Peace is this an indication of a
possible Tha in us China relations or
could this be more of a tactical move by
both sides what might this mean for
India's position I in the evolving
geopolitical landscape so yes uh Trump
recently tweeted or or put out a post in
social media that he had a phone call he
was on a phone call with chairman
shenping president shenping of China in
which both leaders discussed the various
issues like what PR is saying here trade
fentel Tik Tok Global Peace and so on uh
what does this indicate it indicates
nothing it indicates that both leaders
have uh touched a base they have spoken
which leaders should even if you are
leaders of two very hostile Nations it
makes sense to communicate on a on a
reasonably regular basis so that you
know so that there is communication
and there's if there's a communication
breakdown that's the that's where you
have danger signs in a relationship so
even if you're hostile but if you're
communicating regularly then things are
under
control excuse me so I I think it it
only means that India that the US and
China are maintaining that relationship
that we're going to talk to each other
on a on a periodic basis that's all it
doesn't mean there's any Tha or it
doesn't indicate that there's a possible
Tha on the horizon between in the
relations between the two Nations
there's no tactical move or anything
it's just it's just a phone conversation
everybody does it uh and yeah so it it
has no impact on India's position in
this evolving geopolitical landscape
it's just uh routin
curtsy call essentially touching Bay
they the two leaders obviously Mr shei
and Mr Trump know each other they've met
before when Mr Trump was in power in his
is the 45th president and they're just
reconnecting but I don't see Mr Trump uh
because of this one phone conversation
changing his his uh position or views on
China so it it doesn't mean too much we
don't need to read too much into
this prai says again
how could Trump's return reshape India
us relations particularly with defense
trade in the Indo Pacific strategy
gaining more
prominence
so um I think Trump's return is going to
be very interesting and I think he's
going to act as a teacher for the world
he's going to teach the world what the
world has
forgotten what real geopolitics is real
GE geopolitics is all real politic it's
all about hard power there's nothing
soft about this and Trump is is is
there's nothing subtle about Trump he's
going to be very in your
face um and he the best case scenario
for India is that he goes light on India
uh he's obviously going to ride rough
shot over many nations he's going to
probably intensify the trade war against
China which is which is going to hurt
China uh he may definitely
uh want an end to the Ukraine war and he
may be able to negotiate that within a
very short period of time after he comes
to comes to office but that doesn't mean
that in the the relations between the US
and Russia will
improve once Trump acquires it looks
like Greenland and Canada is going to be
really really hard for Russia because
then the US will be a major player in
the Arctic region major player in the
Arctic region bigger player than Russia
certainly if that if this happens so I I
think the Russia is going to feel even
more heat even if the Ukraine war ends
with a
ceasefire so he's going to go after
Russia is going to go after China is
going to go after Canada Greenland
Panama all all these so-called allies
and wasal all his wasal and why do we
think that he may be soft on India he
may go all brutal on India and if if
that happens his friendship with Mr Modi
is of no
consequence in geopolitics there are no
friendships so he could end up trem
really reshaping India us relations he
may give Mr Modi a very simple
ultimatum it's possible this may happen
Okay you either become our wasal or
we're going to treat you just like just
the way we treat China he could do
that so uh
don't live in in in la la land the world
is going to go through a even more
change the next four years than we've
seen in the past 6 seven years you know
sometimes nothing happens for decades
and sometimes decades worth of change
happens in weeks we're going to see that
period now and we're going to see
completely trans completely transformed
geopolitical Lang landscape by the time
Mr Trump is done with the 47th term with
with his
presidency um and it's going to be
the the Imperial of the US that begins
now until now there have been a
superpower a very responsible Nation
rules based world order all this now I
think the naked naked
Imperial uh behavior is going to come
out now with Mr Trump's coming to power
and his presidency most likely is going
to be an inflection point in world
history and American history where the
US transitions from being a responsible
superpower to an outright Imperial power
that crushes everybody that stands in
their way it's very
possible so
that's what I suspect will
happen PR
again could Greenland be a test project
for larger territorial Ambitions with
Japan facing a population crisis do you
think the US might eventually consider
making Japan an official extended
territory to address demographic and
strategic challenges is such a scenario
even
plausible so
look Greenland it's it's not a test
project if the Americans want it they'll
take it and there's nothing Denmark or
the EU can do to stop them they won't
even dare okay all the US has to do is
to land a couple of aircraft there and a
bunch of
soldiers 200 soldiers is enough nobody's
going to stand in their way so if Trump
wants it it's a faith ACC comply it's
done it's done when it comes to Canada
do you think Canada can stop the
Americans from just taking over they're
going to take over if they want to and
and that also May likely happen so it's
not a test project or anything if if
Trump decides this will be done it'll be
done very fast now when it comes to
Japan Japan is indeed facing a terrific
terrible terrible terrible population
crisis uh it's possible that by 2070 or
thereabouts you may not have any
children being born born anymore in
Japan it's possible that that's how bad
things are in Japan and the same can be
said of Korea South Korea as well
so what could the US do about this they
could perhaps if they're still in if
they're still the number one power in
the world they could just take over
Japan they can do whatever they want
with it they occupy Japan militarily
there's nothing that Japanese can do
about any decision of the US so the
Americans may say that the Japanese are
facing this TFR crisis total fertility
rate crisis there's no births happening
anymore let's uh um as a stop Gap
measure or as a corrective measure let's
send immigrants to Japan and that that
process has already begun by the way you
you're seeing immigration into Japan
Japan is allowing immigration and Japan
has historically been extremely Lo to
allow immigration but now the doors seem
to have opened so yeah the Americans may
decide that Japan needs immigrants and
they could send immigrants in that will
totally alter the demographics of Japan
but
uh yeah I'm not sure the Japanese people
will will have much say in this if the
Americans decide to do such a thing so
such a scenario is indeed possible the
Americans can declare Japan in one of
their territories they can do it today
if they want and there's nothing the
thing the world can do about it or the
or the Japanese can do about it so the
Americans can decide whatever they want
by just one stroke of the pen they can
change the entire status of Japan and it
is
definitely scenario that is
plausible okay questions about the
Indian Navy everything and Vador 97
India suddenly commissioned three naval
warships which are Made in India and
commissioned a nuclear submarine last
year too and also the aircraft carrier
recently so how will
it impact India's Maritime
capabilities uh my views on PM modi's
launch of three naval Naval combatants
in Surat nilgiri ands
vager is the Indian Navy the most
powerful navy in the Indian Ocean region
with Growing Power as the US just has
one large base in Diego Garcia as
compared to Pacific Ocean and the
Atlantic Ocean where its Naval strength
is unparalleled and China has cut off a
bit due to the malaka strait and can be
vulnerable in case of War breaks out so
yeah uh a couple of days ago yesterday
the before yesterday or whenever the Mr
Modi Prime Minister Modi inaugurated uh
he launched uh three three
warships the ones that are referred to
over here in the second question down
below and Sur an as nilgiri and as wagir
one of which is a non-nuclear submarine
one of the Scorpion class submarines
so definitely a boost to India's uh
Naval uh strength Naval Firepower and uh
we recently had a nuclear submarine the
second one second operational one that
was commissioned and we also have uh an
aircraft carer that is reasonably new so
all that is going on so yeah it makes
makes India a significant Naval force in
the Indian Ocean region now let's we
haven't seen the map th far it's already
half an hour in so let's take a look at
the map uh give me a second let's let's
put that on the screen the
map so excuse me let's take a look at
the Indian Ocean region so obviously
there's one nation that dominates the
Indian Ocean region which is India it it
juts all the way down almost to the
equator and India is obviously the very
major economy and India has a
significant Naval power which is all
great which is why India is undeniably
a major Naval power in the Indian Ocean
region now let's take a look at the
other powers in the region
Australia is an Indian Ocean Nation but
it's not that powerful it used to be in
the until the 1990s
but Australia Today is nearly a staging
base for the US it's like us-owned
Corporation or us owned territory so
Australia you can see it as a proxy for
the us but uh the Americans don't have
too much Naval assets too much Naval
power deploy in Australia uh then who
else do we have China obviously but
China has cut off from the Indian Ocean
region to a large extent because the of
the malaka sprit they do deploy some
Marines in the Indian Ocean region on
regular petrol patrols routine patrols
but uh they are unable to deploy any
large number of Warships because their
Naval assets are all tied up in the
South China SE region the East China SE
region and because of
the um the island chains and all that
and they have a lot of adversaries in in
this region so they are compelled to uh
deploy their Naval stren strength in
that region in the uh Eastern region the
Philippine Sea the South China Sea and
so on the Sea of Japan not not really
that but they have Pacific Ambitions and
Indian Ocean Ambitions but they still
are unable to operationalize those so
China is to some extent to some extent a
player Iran isn't a very major Naval
power
neither is
Pakistan so and the Americans have like
you
say a base in Diego Garcia now the
Americans have a couple of vasal east
and west Pakistan and they may acquire
that that Island uh that St George or
whatever island it is over
here uh St Martin's Island right they
they may acquire it but that's that may
be in the future so right now they only
have one major base in the region which
is Diego Garcia which is a very major
base of course from which they can
project power and they have a naval base
in
jibuti and I'll not go and show there
but they have the Americans have a very
significant Naval Naval and Military
presence in the uh West Asia region in
Saudi Arabia and Oman this entire
overall region not sure about Oman but
Saudi Arabia definitely very much uh and
so on but
one power that we don't really consider
is France
and France is a major Indian Ocean power
uh you see these islands over here the
French Southern and Antarctic Islands
that's a French
possession uh there's more Islands over
here then you have Runo which is a
French territory it's owned by France
they they have that uh and so the French
also have significant uh a significant
stake in the Indian Ocean region and a
significant Naval presence and India and
France cooperate to a certain extent to
a significant extent of course
navally but you can actually consider
France to be a proxy for the US so
overall if you look at all
this what I could say is that India is
the number two Indian Ocean region power
the number number one power is going to
be the US Naval Naval power despite the
us having very few bases here they still
are the number one Naval power in the
Indian Ocean region and India needs to
invest a lot more in its Navy a lot more
we need numbers quantity has a quanti as
a quality of its own like Joseph Stalin
said so I would say it's a very good
development that we have launched three
new warships but I think we need at
least 30 to 50 new more warships uh we
need to have a submarine strength of
minimum 30 I would say which means that
we have at any given point in time 10 10
that are deployed operationally because
here's the deal in in Naval assets if
you have three naval assets at only any
given point in time only one is deployed
where it needs to be one is either being
refitted and another one is either
coming back to base or coming from base
to the deployment region that's the rule
of thumb for Navy if you have three
assets only one is deployed at any given
point in time so if you have 30 submarin
you can deploy 10 on a best case
scenario if you have what 15 or so like
we have it means at any given point in
time we may have maximum 45 deployed
which is a bad State of Affairs so India
needs lots of submarines and we are very
slowly at snail space going in the
direction uh we need to uh hasten
up okay Sun Moon says uh why why are
some political analysts debunking the
Deep State well I'm not aware of who
debunking or not or or claiming it
doesn't exist but uh recently Trump put
out statement in a video about what he's
going to do about the Deep State and how
he's going to dismantle the Deep state
so when the US president talks about the
Deep State I mean that's that's the most
powerful uh office in the world right it
it has its own
credibility he's the president-elect but
he's a former president and is soon
going to be the president again so when
he says something it's credible right
and he was talking about the Deep State
now here's the deal when he spoke about
the deep deep State he wasn't see when I
talk about what they call the Deep state
I'm talking about an extra governmental
extra electoral extra Democratic Center
of power that is kind of
permanent and that is more powerful than
the US government and the US president
and it's very clear by now that that
that does exist I me Biden and Kamala
Harris were not in power I mean they
were in office they were never in power
somebody else was was running the
country so when Trump says I'm going to
go after the Deep State and he talks
about cutting down cutting down on the
bureaucracy pruning the bureaucracy he's
trying to claim that the bureaucracy is
the Deep state so he's trying to
obfuscate what the Deep State really is
right so the Deep State clearly exists
you can call it the Deep State you can
call it whatever you want the
establishment or the swamp whatever you
want to call it but it does exist
there's no question about it a bunch of
very small number of very very powerful
people very wealthy people who have
turned wealth and power into
interchangeable fible commodities
and we don't know who they are but they
clearly do exist this small grouping of
people maybe a mediumsized grouping of
people we don't know who they are and
they never go out of office or power
because they're never in office they're
an extra Democratic Power Center
permanent power center and that's not
the bureaucracy so I don't care what
experts say don't say so-called
political analyst and all it doesn't
matter we we can see that certain things
do seem to exist makes sense that it
exists so
and even Trump tried to reframe what the
Deep state is and and you know but yeah
it is what it
is Summit statement says America is too
much pro Israel then why did the US let
Pakistan have nukes also Israel wanted
to attack uh the kahuta base via India
Khan Abdul Kad Khan's base in kahuta by
India why would want Israel want to
destroy something that is supported by
the biggest Ally of the US say this is a
very interesting
question so um yeah the US is is is uh
an
unconditional Ally of the of of Israel
no matter what Israel does the Americans
will support Israel you can take out the
US's Liberty and smash it to smin it's
okay A bunch of US Sailors are killed
doesn't matter the US will still support
Israel um so now so that is is indeed
the
case now what happened what happens is
that uh despite the US always being an
unconditional supporter of Israel the
interests and agendas of of the two
Nations can
differ so uh the
US what happened in the 20th century is
that the Indian government Neu
regime veered it it uh veered very
strongly in the in in the direction of
the
USSR so India kind of became a us a USSR
vasal it did yeah and once that happens
the Americans will be really alarmed and
they will try and play their own games
and and cultivate their own vasal in the
region and that's why they cultivated
Pakistan as a
vasal so they turned Pakistan into a us
wasal they funded and financed Pakistani
terrorism in Afghanistan India etc for
decades we know that that's that's all
old history but they also ensure that
Pakistan that when
Pakistan's the scientist Abdul Kad Khan
stole nuclear Blueprints and Technology
Etc from Europe the Americans looked the
other way they allowed this to happen
and there was some Chinese involvement
also because the Chinese uh passed on
some nuclear uh weapon technology which
had been tested in Tibet lnur which
apparently was North Korean design so
the Americans the Chinese they
collaborated they colluded in turning
Pakistan into a nuclear power and you
know that the Americans and the Chinese
were on the same page after the visit of
Nixon and Kissinger in the 1970s uh to
China when maung was still
alive um and India and China were also
not on good terms so it made sense for
them to collude when it comes to
Pakistan so they ensure that Pakistan
becomes nuclear becomes a nuclear power
a defacto nuclear power or or or an
Undeclared nuclear power by the 1980s
maybe the early or mid 1980s okay
now so Israel obviously their eyes and
ears are everywhere and this alarms
them and the Israelis often do things
that the Americans don't want them to do
and then they say okay now deal with it
so what the israelit decided was that
they would bomb so in I think 1981 the
Israelis had bombed the osirak reactor
in Iraq Iraq Saddam Hussein's Iraq and
that destroyed s's hopes and Ambitions
of becoming a nuclear weapons power of
of Iraq becoming a nuclear weapons power
and now the pakistanis were developing
the kahuta reactor so the Israelis want
wanted to destroy that as well so the
Israelis talked to the uh government of
India Mrs Gandhi's government and it was
decided that there would be Israeli
planes that will take off from India
maybe from Jam nagar maybe from
from somewhere in Punjab or
something they will um go around the
Himalayas use the Himalayas as a shield
and then enter Pakistani airspace and
take out the reactor so a bunch of f16s
with f-15s for protection that sort of
thing and this almost went ahead once or
maybe on a couple of occasions but the
Americans intervened and told I don't
know what they told the Israelis but the
Israelis pulled out of this entire uh
Mission this
project so what we don't know what was
discussed between the Americans and the
Israelis I don't we don't know what the
Americans told the Israelis and what uh
promises the Israelis extracted or or
did
not but there was the end of it and
after that there was no Indian attempt
to take out the reactor in kahuta and
the Israelis stayed out of the matter so
it looks like they got Assurance the is
it looks like the Israel has got an
assurance from the US that Pakistani
nuclear weapons will never be used
against
you
okay now that's what apparently happened
that's what I think happened and today
even today 2025 there's a question mark
on what is the real relationship between
Israel and Pakistan you know the
pakistanis condemn Israel they know they
do Pak that Israel is this or that or
whatever and what they're doing in Gaza
is reprehensible and terrible and all
that but do they ever take an actual any
actual action against Israel I have
always for the past I don't know how
many years
emphasizing the difference between words
and
actions just condemning something
verbally makes no difference in the
world it's just a bunch of words it
doesn't hurt a nation the pakistanis
have never done anything that can
actually hurt hurt Israel's interests
ever right so the the question is what
is the relationship between Pakistan and
is roel today Pakistan is a us vasal
that's a US client
State ever since Imran Khan was oued and
thrown into jail and whoever else came
to power came to office ever since that
day Pakistan is firmly a us
wasal
okay and the US is Israel's number one
supporter so one is the us wasal and one
is the US's number one
Ally so clearly these two the wasal and
the Ally cannot be enemies makes no
sense my question is today as of today
2025 what is the relationship between
Israel and
Pakistan they I I'll assure you the two
Nations we know that they don't have
diplomatic connection relations
diplomatic ties but I assure you there
will be some track to track track three
diplomacy going on at some levels
between the two
Nations so it's a complicated world it's
a complicated relationship and the
Israelis have been given the assurance
that Pakistani weapons Pakistani nukes
will never ever be used against them in
any circumstances if that Assurance was
not there and if the Israelis did not
believe the Assurance they would have
taken out Pakistan's nuclear weapons
power program at the first possible
opportunity which was in the early 80s
and they would not have
tolerated Pakistan becoming an actual
demonstrated nuclear weapons power they
would not have tolerated that they know
it will now be used against them they
have that
Assurance vickram geopolitical says
Russia has selected India to construct
its four non-nuclear ice breaker ships
valued $750 million why has Russia
chosen India instead of China
well good question interesting question
what's an icebreaker an icebreaker is a
ship with a reinforced Hull that can uh
that can Ram through sheet ice which you
know if you go to the Arctic or
Antarctic regions part of the earth
there are in the in the Arctic Circle
you essentially have permanent ice over
there that floats over the
ocean and if you want a ship to navigate
that region or if you want a ship to go
to Antarctica you have to plow through
hundreds of square kilometers of just
sheet ice floating over over
water and that's like essentially
icebergs but just one sheet of icebergs
and you know what happens when ships hit
icebergs right you know what happened to
the Titanic the ship struck an iceberg
and
sank so that's dangerous that's deadly
for ships you know colliding with a
block of ice but you have a class of
ships called ice breakers that have very
strong reinforced HS that can simply cut
through the ice
that's what an icebreaker is and the
Russian Russians they obviously the the
nation of Russia is an Arctic nation and
now the Arctic uh region is beginning to
thaw because of global warming and all
that so the Arctic region will soon
become a a viable uh trade route and
shipping shipping route but it it will
still have a significant amount of of
you know time when it's ice
bound so to navigate the region you need
ice
breakers and and that's why Russia needs
to acquire more ice breakers they've
always been a nation with that operates
multiple ice breakers I don't know how
many dozens but yeah they need more
newer ones so they have commissioned
India apparently to construct four of
these non-nuclear ice breakers you can
even have nuclear powered ice breakers
uh so the question is why India uh why
not China the Chinese also have a
excellent world class ship building
industry and there are other nations as
well so first of all the European
nations are out of the question now
because of the war in Ukraine and the
whole of Western Europe is against
Russia so France or other nations they
wanton do this for Russia the US is
absolutely out of the question obviously
uh South Korea is a us wasal a US Clan
state so they won't do it for Russia
neither will Japan which is a US
possession us occupied territory Japan
also won't do it for Russia so the only
options left major options are India and
China and apparently China's shipyards
are are occupied until I don't know what
27 28 maybe 2030 thereabouts that's why
the Russians have chosen India so good
for Russia good for India good for the
relationship and that's probably why
they have chosen India to uh take up
this
project Vikram geopolitical asks how
will China react to the five to the $450
million India Indonesia brahmos deal or
will it not react considering that that
share of the deal also goes to
Russia okay um let's be realistic about
the brahmos
missile okay would you like to hear some
truths about the brahmas missile it's a
great missile yeah we know that it was
the world's fastest cruise missile 20
years
ago it was the world's fastest cruise
missile until the 2010s the first half
today you have cruise missiles that far
exceed the speed of brahos so the
brahmos is still a great missile but
it's by no means the best missile in the
world best Cru missile in the world
anymore okay and you will have Nations
like China that may possibly have
developed some kind of defense against
the brahmos or a brahos kind of missile
brahmos class
missile p y class
missile okay um of course um if India
were to sell 10,000 brahmos missiles to
Indonesia that would set off a billion
alarm bells in China but if you sell
$500 million worth of brahmas missiles
it's not going to alarm China too much
and China and Indonesia don't have a
very hostile relationship of course
China
does claim Indonesian territories than N
I don't know what islands they claim
Indonesian territory also so but that's
okay uh so this sale of about $500
million worth of brahmos missiles won't
really alarm China and of course Russia
will also get cut off the share because
Russia is a is is a stakeholder in
brahmos so I don't think it will alarm
China too much this
deal uh so yeah that's how I see it and
please understand the brahos is no
longer the world's best cruise missile
um I think the
siron is now the world's deadliest
cruise missile uh it it it's a mark 9 or
Mark 10 missile the brahmas is Mark 2 so
you're going to have a brahos Next
Generation which would be a lighter
missile uh perhaps Hypersonic which is
Mark 5 plus I'm not sure what the deal
is I don't know how long it'll take
maybe sooner maybe later I'm not sure
but the brahos is no longer the scariest
missile in the world it's still a
deadly uh weapon to have in your Arsenal
for sure
but yeah that's where we are
today adik says can you do a video on
African geopolitics future I'd love to
do that you know Africa is a region that
really interests me very much and uh for
whatever reason very few people care
to look at Africa understand what's
happening there and uh make videos about
Africa or whatever uh uh I'm one of the
people who is genuinely interested in
Africa and I've made some videos about
Africa uh last couple of years you
had uh a number of
cou um so I had covered that in in the
Sahel region in Burkina
Faso uh and so on the ni the ner coup
the whatever was happening there coup in
ner and there's a whole situation in in
that region burkinafaso and all that the
ecoas uh region so I have made a few
videos about that and I would love to
continue doing that now Africa is
obviously a gigantic continent it's the
largest continent the world the the
planet has and so many nations so many
cultures so many different geopolitical
scenarios so many climatic climatic
regions U so it's it's hard to make one
video about the entire geopolitical
future of the entire continent but you
can take it from a region to region
basis maybe East Africa West Africa
southern Africa the Sahel region uh
central Africa Northern Africa you can
do it separately and I would love to do
that as in when the need or opportunity
arises uh or maybe I could just do a few
explan videos about what the different
regions of Africa are and all that so uh
I would say that yeah it's a great
suggestion thank you for the suggestion
and I certainly will love to do that
going yep in the
future okay Shankar Kar says
Norman French was the official court
language of the English crown since the
time William became king So how and when
did the transition of of French to
English as the court language happen in
English Monarchy was it during the twoo
era okay interesting question we're
talking about history now so
uh so you right Norman French became the
official court language of English
uh from the year 1066 onwards the year
1066 was the year that William the
bastard became William the Conqueror
okay he was an illegitimate son of his
father and his father had to go on a
crusade and he had no legitimate
children so he was forced to declare
that his illegitimate son William was
the hair to his to the to the Dukey of
Normandy to become the next Duke of
Normandy if he did not come back
from The Crusade and as it happened he
died in The Crusade or on the way or
wherever so this young boy I don't know
he was 11 12 whatever his age was he was
illegitimate he became the Duke of
Normandy and for the rest of his career
for a significant portion of his life he
was called William the
bastard but the year 1066 he crossed the
English Channel with a bunch of ships
and he
landed where did he land Hastings yeah
probably
Hastings no Stamford Bridge
one of these two battles and the poor
English
King
Harold he had to fight two battles in a
week once against one battle against the
the the the Vikings led by uh haral
hardrada and a traitor brother Harold's
own brother so he wins that battle he
gives Harold hard what he asked for six
feet of land in England and then he he's
word that a Norman Force has landed all
the way down south so he has to March
his exhausted Army hundreds of
kilometers all the way down south and
then he meets uh
William uh at Hastings I believe and
yeah he gets unlucky he catches an arrow
in his eye and that's that's the story
uh so that's how uh the Normans
conquered England the last time England
that is the last time ever that England
was successfully conquered the year
1066 and that's the year that Norman
French becomes uh the official court
language so before that uh before Norman
French you had the Anglo-Saxon language
that which is Old English that was the
court language in France and
uh Britain was was invaded by by Angles
and Saxons two Germanic tribes around
410 or so ad okay the the leaders of the
of the invador were hangist and horsa
the stallion and the horse so that's
when the Anglo-Saxon language entered
England okay before that you had Latin
the language of the Romans because the
Romans had conquered England starting
with Julius Caesar so Latin was the
official court language as long as the
Romans were there and before the Romans
arrived in England you had various
Celtic languages that were or bronic
languages pictish Scottish bronic Celtic
language Etc which were the official
court languages which would have been
the official court languages so
1066 Norman French becomes the court
language now what happens
is and it Remains the court language of
and the prestige language the language
of the Elites for at least at least a
couple of centuries for example one of
the greatest of the English kings is
Richard the lionart right he lived in
the 12th century ad the son of uh Henry
II and El of
aktin and Richard the lionard spoke
Norman French or French he spoke French
and His Banner his his flag was the OA
Lions so French was the language of the
elites it was the court language it was
a Prestige language it was considered to
be prestigious to speak French uh now by
the 13th
century uh the language had kind of
changed the Norman French
language spoken by the elites had
changed considerably the syntax had
become much more like English and some
of them some of these Nobles just gave
up Norman French and started speaking
English uh now so in the 14th century so
at this time you have Middle English the
Anglo-Saxon language before William was
Old English by the 14th century you have
something called Middle English and one
of the most important works of English
literature is the canab Tales written by
Joffrey Schauer which was written in the
14th century and it was written in
Middle English one of the most important
Works in English literature and uh it's
it's a it's it depicts a storytelling
contest by a group of pilgrims as they
traveled together from London to
Canterbury okay to visit the the the
shrine of a Saint Thomas Becket at
Canterbury Cathedral Thomas Beckett was
a a Troublesome or meddlesome or
turbulent priest who was assassinated
stabbed in the 12th century in the
second half of the 12th century ad and
he was assassinated because the king the
father of Richard the lionart Henry II
he said to No One In general will no one
get no will no one rid me of this
Troublesome priest so he said this in
his court with his Knights present but
he he did not order anybody to go and
assassinate the guy but it was
considered to be an order and a couple
of his guys went ahead and did the
assassination so that I'm digressing now
it's a different
story uh so in The 14th Century Middle
English was spoken by the people of
England but Norman French was still kind
of the elite language or the prestige
language then in the 14th and 15th
centuries you had the 100-year war
between England and France
it uh it was set off when the king of
England made a claim to the throne of
France because the French King died
without leaving in air and all that so
during this 100-year war between England
and France French came to be seen as the
language of the enemy and that's when
you know the whole tide changed the
everything the tide turned and uh the
the aristocracy the elites also adopted
Middle English as as the court language
uh so you're talking about the Tor era
obviously so you had a transition from
uh the Norman era which is uh the
lineage of of Henry the of William the
Conqueror which still exists today every
single king or queen since 1066 ad has
been a descendant direct descendant of
William the Conqueror but there was this
uh period which was which was the Norman
period when the kings were outright
Normans kings and queens were outright
Normans
then you had uh the plantagenet
era uh their last king was Richard III
the the guy with the Hunchback he had
scoliosis his skeleton was recently
discovered after half a millennium in
obscurity so the last plantagenet king
died in the Battle of bossworth
bossworth field he lost to Henry the 7th
Henry Tudor and that's the beginning of
the Tudor period which starts in the
late 1400s and
goes all the way to the beginning of the
17th century which included the era the
Elizabethan era so that's the Tudor
period in which the court language was
was whatever English was spoken at the
time Middle English or whatever but uh
it's not during the Tudor era that the
uh language changed it changed during
the 100 Years War Between the English
and the French that's the 13th that's
the 14th and 15th centuries but very
interesting uh question because it tells
you it shows you how languages change
languages evolve you had Celtic
languages then you had Latin then you
had the Anglo-Saxon language Old English
then you had the Norman French period
Then you had Middle English and then you
have uh Shakespearean English and then
present day English very interesting
uh mechanics and dynamics of change
linguistic change societal change and so
on
okay mus says previously you spoke about
similarities between Indra and the
European gods of Thunder like pirun zus
Thor Etc in Christianity there's a Saint
George the Victorious or St George it's
a man on a horse killing a snake or a
dragon depends depends on the version of
the story but with a spear not with
thunder it's not a thunderbolt it's not
a hammer it's spear the Indo European
gods have the vajra or the Thunderbolt
which is also a hammer right so uh St
George has a is a Christian Legend it's
unimpressive at least because barely
anyone knows it but everyone knows the
image of George the small frame Fame of
the Legend doesn't match the enormous
respect and widespread and widespread
the image has at all the image of of St
George is everywhere Russia
Georgia which probably got its external
name because of the huge respect to the
Saint in these lands it's in it's in
Rome it's in Western Europe including
British
lands and it's not only a religious
symbol but a state symbol as well do you
think it's the same image as these
ancient gods or am I wrong please take a
look and I advise you to enjoy the
amazing golden Memorial of St George
from tiil Georgia all right thank you
I'll check it out if I can okay we're
talking about
uh we're talking about St
George so St George was a Christian was
a Roman soldier during his lifetime and
he died sometime in the beginning of the
4th Century
ad um and he is venerated as one of the
great Saints of Christianity
now um let's Google it let's let's see
the the image the iconography shall we
uh let us go to
Google and we shall Google St George and
the Dragon right yes where's Google here
it is St George and the Dragon
so what's it look
like so here is the classical
iconography the classical image stain
George on this on the Steed on the horse
he's got the spear and he is Spearing
this dragon and you have various
representations of this uh of this
legend or this myth right St George and
and there's this lady over here so
that's the that's the that's the story
so the story is that um the story is
that
there was this
dragon that was terrorizing the people
of a town in Libya North Africa during
the lifetime of of St George okay that's
a story and to to appease the dragon the
people of the
Town had to sacrifice a livestock sheep
or whatever to the dragon every day and
eventually they unfortunately ran out of
livestock so then they had to uh so then
they had to resort to sacrificing humans
now so they would decide every day or
whenever by consensus that so and so
person will be chosen and then one day
it was the turn of the of the daughter
of the king the
princess and so she had to do her Duty
so she goes to the place where the
Dragon lives and on the way over there
she's crying obviously because she's
going to her death and she meets this
guy the St George and George asks her
why are you crying and she says that I'm
going to to the place where the dragon
is and I advise you to please run away
because the dragon will will kill you
otherwise and St JN says no how can I
allow this to happen I'll go and meet
the dragon and so according to the to
the myth he goes and fights the dragon
and he Spears the dragon from his horse
and he kills the dragon and saves the
the the the the princess and the city
that's the myth okay and it's a very
powerful and very uh that sort of
story and St George is one of the most
venerated Saint in
Christianity now like like mus white
says over here it's it's it's not merely
a religious symbol it's a state symbol
as well now what does he mean by this
it's a very important point he makes and
let's go back to the screen now it's a
very important point he makes let's put
this back on the screen but now we're
going to say St George
cross and this is what I mean by the St
George's cross see this I'm sure you've
seen it somewhere it's the official flag
of
England okay St George cross Indian
Navy check this out this is the flag of
the Indian Navy or it used to be at
least I hope it's no longer the case but
I mean Independent India was still
holding on to
this to this invasive
thing so the St George cross is a it's
the
emblem or flag of England uh so now the
question is is the St George myth a
continuation or an appropriation of the
pre-christian uh Indo-European Mythos of
Indra or Thor or
Peron or or Jupiter or Zeus fighting the
the sea monster which was originally
vitra so Indra fight fights vitra that's
the oldest version of the story of of
the story The Ric times then you have
Jupiter fighting Typhon you have Zeus
Jupiter comes later Zeus fights tyon and
Jupiter also fights a sea monster then
and so on long
story so is is the St George story with
the dragon a continuation or
appropriation of the Indo
European uh myth is the question I don't
think it is the case I'll tell you what
it actually is uh the St George uh let's
go back St
George and the Dragon so you see this a
Horseman on with with a spear and
spearing a reptile that's
actually an an image that you see that's
very old it's the thran traan horse man
you see this so th now you'll ask me
what is th and I actually should tell
you what th is so let's first go to the
map and I'll show you what th is Trace
is a geographical
region if you go to Turkey okay turkey
so turkey is a nation that's like 90% in
Asia and about about 5% let's say in
Europe and the division the boundary
between Europe and Asia is supposed to
be uh the straight of the dardanel and
the straight of the BOS the bosor strait
which passes through Istanbul so half of
Istanbul is in Asia half is in Europe so
if you look at the European portion of
turkey okay west of Istanbul west of
Constantinople that region was the
historical region of
thce and uh it was you could say a
region where during the Roman times you
had skians who lived there the European
skians the majority the skians lived in
Asia many of them in India as well but
you had European skians who lived here
so th was was the is this region and it
is from there that you have that you get
this iconography of the thran horsemen
let's put that back on the screen thran
Horsemen so this is The thran Horseman
as you can see it's a guy on a horse and
he is brandishing a spear and over here
you will see that he is going towards a
tree on which there is this big snake
right there's a snake that is entwined
around a tree and he is going after that
that that snake and you will see that in
multiple images the snake the snake
thing this is a broken
version sometimes it is him spearing a
crocodile in this case you have a
crocodile in other cases over here also
you have a snake so this is the original
image that was
reappropriated or or rather appropriated
by the chrisan you have a snake here as
well you see the UNESCO image so that's
a thian Horseman and I think that's the
one that was taken as the template from
from on from which the St George myth
was
created so it's not Indra or or or
Jupiter or Zeus this time or Peron it's
the thran horsemen so see Christianity
was this new artificial religion that
came up came up uh about 2,000 years ago
and and it was imposed on Europe by
force by through a considerable amount
of violence and what they they did was
they appropriated uh pre-christian
religions and traditions and superimpose
Christianity on those because people
were used to celebrating festivals on
certain dates so they reappropriated and
recycled those dates as Christian
festivals and the and they appropriated
some iconography some some Legends and
turned them into Christian Legends so
this is an example of that St George and
the Dragon it's it's nothing but an
appropriation of the thran horsemen U
legend or myth or whatever it is but
yeah it's a very interesting uh question
that you asked oh
here G of jat mum says I am following
the understanding America podcast of
which two episodes have come out thus
far loads of interesting information in
it and I love it thank you very much
thank you very much um a question which
arises into one's mind is is that who
are the Native Americans the Aztecs the
Incas the Mayas the Mohawks the inates
the chov the K the beuk and so on so
forth so many different tribal groups
the the
Apache um so on so forth so who are the
Native Americans what's their origin is
the question right are they step people
how do they end up in that part of the
world now for to answer this question we
have to obviously take a look at the map
um right where's the map let's that on
the screen so there's a number of
schools of of of his you know schools of
thought over
here so one school of thought so the
the the majority consensus for a very
long time has been that you had an we
know that we had an Ice Age about which
ended about 11 or 12,000 years before
today okay and the Ice Age lasted at
least 10 15,000 years what was the last
glacial glacial minimum was about 20,000
,000 BC or something around that time
you can look at them okay I don't have
it memorized but during the Ice Age this
region of the world the bearing straight
region was completely iced over which
means that there was a land bridge
between
Asia and North
America um and it is believed that there
was a migration from Asia into North
America over this land bridge and if you
look at the facial features the
phenotypes of the Native Americans
wherever they live North America Central
America or South America they look kind
of like you know from their facial
features they look like people from
Eastern Asia or
Mongolia that that that those facial
features are are pretty uh clear to see
you can see the similarities there so
the mainstream school of thought is that
during the last ice age there was a
migration over land over this ice Bridge
land bridge from Asia West from Eastern
Asia North Eastern Asia into
Northwestern America into Alaska and all
that and then eventually over the
Millennia as the ice sheets uh dissolved
and disappeared then the migrants came
further south and eventually they came
down all the way to the southernmost
part of South America and that process
apparently according to this school of
thought took thousands of years
uh and it's it's pretty clear that there
are genetic similarities between various
uh Native American uh ethnic groups and
the peoples of of uh Siberia Mongolia
Etc it's pretty clear that this is
indeed the case so that is uh the
mainstream consensus that this is what
happened but we have also discovered
human remains or or evidence of human
presence in South America that goes back
more than a 100,000
years now how do you fit that into the
prevailing uh consensus you
can't so it's possible there could have
been multiple waves of migration into
the Americas maybe so we know that look
you know how Australia was settled it
was settled from from Africa about 60 or
70,000 years ago people from Africa I
don't know how they reached Australia
but they I think they sailed across the
ocean the Indian Ocean it must have been
an incredible journey or maybe they went
island hopping or whatever and some of
them got struck in the and mon maybe
that's also a possibility but it was an
epic migration so if they could do that
and if and we also know that people have
migrated over the centuries to far off
places like like Hawaii like French
Polynesia uh to hungara which is Easter
Island and so on then it's also possible
that they could have migrated to South
America or North America maybe from
Africa maybe from somewhere else and we
have evidence of human presence in South
America that goes back more than 100,000
years so
uh so we don't know for sure but one
thing is clear that a lot of these uh
Native American ethnic groups have
genetic Affinity or or similarities with
the people of Northeast Asia the
Siberian people and the mongolic people
that is indeed the case so this is still
a work in progress like everything else
uh the more research we do the more
evidence turns up the better an
understanding we have of what happened
in the past uh so yeah that's what
that's what I can offer you as as of
now himansu Sharma says I'm studying at
a Canadian College in our culture and
diversity class today we learned that
the indigenous people of Canada of North
America did not have any kind of
Healthcare System back in the day
doctors first arrived with the European
settlers who cared for the sick at their
homes built hospitals and churches let's
not omit the churches and established a
robust Health Care system in America can
you please shed some light on this
okay let me let me Google something okay
and and I'll put that on the screen I'll
do it in real time for you to
see okay here we are
Google Louis pastor
Discovery discovered bacteria which year
1878 Lou pter discovered bacteria that's
the first time we understood in the
whole world that something like bacteria
exists as far as we know okay before
Louie pastor's discovery of bacteria all
medicine was mumbo
jumbo there was no concept of
sterilization there was no understanding
of what caused diseases
just a couple of centuries three
centuries or whatever before Louis P you
had the Black Death ravaging through
Europe and people had no idea what was
causing
it uh when was the Black Death let's
let's Google that also right just to
just to be sure so Louis pter discovers
bacteria in
1878 Black Death Europe uh
year
1351 1351 and this is 1878 so it's about
about 500 years ago 500 years there's a
gap of about 500 years in from 13 uh
from 1351 to 1878 there was no
significant improvement in our
understanding of what causes disease and
illness of course you
know surgical techniques would have
improved and all that but uh most people
don't need
surgery most people when they feel sick
when they fall sick they need medicine
which is either antiviral or
antibacterial
right and that wasn't there the first
antibiotics were discovered after Louis
past's discovery of bacteria maybe in
the early 20th century of
thereabouts so the
Europeans when they started coming to
the Americas it starts with with
Columbus and then the
Spaniards and the whole story is there
and then the the French the hinos and
and then the English and all they come
in the 16 17th Cent and all that and
when they come to North America they
don't have any understanding of medicine
it's not like they have world class icus
and whatnot H what you have in today's
well equipped hospitals they have none
of that they have the most primitive
understanding of
medicine so what Health Care system did
they provide for the indigenous people
what joke what kind of joke is this even
in the 19th
century the healthcare system of the
Europeans in the West
was super rudimentary so all these
claims that these people make that they
brought C see the claim at the end of
the day is to justify what they did to
the
people
um about 100 million Native Americans
were
killed North Plus South
America okay 100 million and the you
will they will claim that much of this
was because of diseases and the
Europeans did not mean to do this to
them it just happened because the
natives did not have any uh immunity
towards its diseases well if you had
such a great health care System then
maybe you could have vaccinated them or
done something something about their
suffering nothing nothing right so the
facts don't support the claims that are
being made over here what Health Care
system did the Europeans bring to the
Americas doctors there were no doctors
they were they were shamans they were
Voodoo practitioners right Hospital what
a joke uh all this is is done to to kind
of justify or or or
or um you know we know what the
Europeans did to to make themselves feel
better they they they spin such
yards okay um to to give them to give
yourself some moral Comfort or emotional
comfort that you know we tried our best
and all that the truth is that there was
a genocide in the Americas and the
Europeans did
that so and that some of that continues
even now do you know what a Starlight
since we talking about
Canada okay since we are talking about
Canada I might I may as well do
this okay let's Google
this they they did such so much good for
the natives right what's a Starlight to
tour yeah what's a Starlight tour in
Canada there we have it Saskatoon
freezing
deaths the Saskatoon freezing deaths
involved indigenous Canadians in and
immediately outside sason sasan in the
1990s and early 2000s that's like day
before yesterday early 2000s so
apparently it went on until the 1990s
and early 2000s and now it no longer
happens you're going to buy that
nonsense okay so this happened in the
1990s early 2000s and are suspected of
being linked to actions by members of
the Saskatoon Police
Service police officers would arrest
indigenous people who are usually male
for alleged drunkenness and or
disorderly Behavior alleged sometimes
without cause the officers would then
drive these people to the outskirts of
the city at night during winter and
abandon them leaving them stranded in
subzero temperatures which would
inevitably lead to the person dying of
being frozen to
death this practice is known as taking
indigenous people on Starlight tours and
dates back to at least 7
1976 as of 2021 despite convictions for
related offenses no police officer has
been
specifically convicted for having caused
freezing deaths okay I'm just giving you
an very high level overview this sort of
thing still
happens the native people in Canada in
in the Americas are still treated like
third class
citizens so all these stories that they
put out these are lies these are
falsehoods there was genocide and there
still is
terrible um marginalization and and
victimization of the native people of
North America and it's a it's a it's a
shame it's a
Pity
right vicam geopolitical says Russia has
invited India to join the aan quad will
India join an organization which also
includes Pakistan or is Russia planning
to replace Pakistan with India and the
members of the Quad will be Russia China
Iran and
India
okay so this Russia this this Afghan
quad is a Russia China initiative and is
part of the Shanghai cooperation
organization the SEO it's a subset or
subgrouping within the Shanghai
cooperation
organization now to understand why you
have these four nations all you have to
do is to look at the map so I I'll help
you out with that where is the map okay
we go to the map I'm going to put the
map on the screen and let me explain why
you have these four nations so let's
zoom in
to the Indian subcontinent Northwest you
have Afghanistan here now which are the
Nations that Afghanistan has land
borders with
Pakistan
Iran a bunch of south of Central Asian
Nations which is Tajikistan usbekistan
and
turkistan and then you have
uh then you have the wakan corridor that
touches Tibet or or sang of China and
the connection with India doesn't exist
right now because some this territory is
po so the major Nations over here are
Pakistan Iran
China and three Central Asian Nations
now in Central Asia the real power that
actually exists over here is is Russia
so that's why you have Russia Iran
Pakistan and China that are involved in
the afan quad right and India is not
because India doesn't really have a land
border right now with Afghanistan
despite it being on the map but in on on
the ground it's not there so that's why
you have these three nations
now so why has India in why has Russia
invited India to join the quad the
Afghan quad it's because
um India is actively involved
diplomatically and in other ways with
the government in Afghanistan the
Taliban government we have reasonably
good relations uh our diplomats recently
met the a an Afghan a high level Afghan
delegation uh with the Afghan foreign
minister Taliban foreign minister in
Dubai like just a week or so ago so we
are actively engaging with the Taliban
we have good relations the Tali the
pakistanis don't have good relations
with the Taliban with with
Afghanistan uh and India is a
well-wisher of Afghanistan
Pakistan isn't and the Russians would
want India to be more involved and maybe
India may have requested them to involve
uh to invite India to participate in
this matter and right now the
relationship between between India and
China is also kind of improving
hopefully it continues that way so maybe
China also is okay with that and doesn't
have an issue the only nation that would
have an issue with this would be
Pakistan so it makes sense for India to
be involved India is it's it's uh its
relevance globally and regionally is is
increasing and it's India is a force for
stability a Force for good unlike
Pakistan Pakistan is a us wasal which is
which means it is
untrustworthy from the Russian and CH as
well as Chinese perspective from India's
perspective it has always been
untrustworthy uh so that's why the
Russians may be inviting India will
India join I think it makes sense for
India to be involved in anything that is
concerned with the well-being of
Afghanistan in the stability of the
region I think it it may make sense for
India to join will Russia replace
Pakistan with India you can't replace
Pakistan because Pakistan has a
significantly long border with
Afghanistan and whatever happens in the
region Pakistan has has to be involved
so I think the quad may become a pentad
or something it may be five nations
going forward if India does indeed
accept this invitation or Pakistan won't
be removed as far as I can as far as I
see right
geopolitical dub says in a group
discussion someone asked me to choose
between the bhagwad Gita and the
constitution of India and I chose the
bhagwad Gita but this person got
frustrated and started saying that you
are not loyal to India and so on did I
do anything wrong by choosing the bhagat
Gita over the constitution of
India
look there is no law in India but says
that you have to choose the stitution
over every other
book
okay and if you talking
about a text being Indian or less Indian
which text is more Indian historically
culturally
civilization is the constitution of
India more Indian or is the bhagwat Gita
more Indian the constitution of India
was created in
1947 by by repurposing the 1935
government of India Act created by the
British and copy pasting a whole bunch
of stuff from other other constitutions
there's absolutely nothing Indian about
the constitution of
India the constitution of India has not
been ratified by the people of India the
people of India were never given a
chance to ratify the
Constitution it has been shoved down the
throats of the people of India and you
are being taught that it's your
Constitution the bhagwat Gita is a
civilization document that's been our
civilization document for thousands of
years
if you ask me to
choose between the bhagwat Gita and the
Constitution I would of course choose
the bhagwat Gita the constitution of
India needs to be replaced actually it
is not serving any purpose for India it
is
not you know there are Hindu phobic
closes in the constitution of
India articles something to something
which are explicitly anti-hindu
why would anybody choose the
Constitution over the over the bhagwat
Gita and how does it make you anti
Indian we India needs a new constitution
a constitution is not some holy book it
was made a made by a bunch of Indians
bunch of people to whom power was handed
by the British extra democratically
undemocratically and they never allowed
the people of India to ratify it which
is either to accept or reject the
Constitution so
uh ideally we need a better Constitution
a way better Constitution a constitution
that is Indian in value
we don't have that right now so I would
anytime choose the bhagwat Gita which is
a genuinely Indian
text and it's one of the best texts in
the
world vickram geopolitical says a
biotech company called colosal
biosciences has raised $200 million to
bring back extinct animals to life is
this possible with the help of AI
genetic engineering and scientific
knowledge that we humans currently
process
possess it's it's possible some of it is
possible look it may still be completely
farfetched to bring dinosaurs back to
life for
example the question is how do we do
this right U let's say I have a let's
say I have $200 million and I have a lab
with the best technicians and
bioengineers geneticists and all
that now how do I bring an extinct
animal back to
life whichever extinct animal I want to
bring back to life I first of all I will
need it's DNA it's uncorrupted un
un contaminated
DNA which means that I will need to find
this animal a specimen of this animal in
a frozen State maybe from the Perma
Frost or whatever and one such animal is
the woly mammoth which went extinct
about 10,000 years ago Homo sapiens
hunted it out of
existence that's what we believe now you
do find Frozen mammoths from time to
time in the Siberian permafrost in
various parts
of the
world Siberia Etc so we have good
reasonably good frozen specimens we uh
in time to time they find Frozen
mammoths Frozen M what mountain lions or
saber-tooth tigers or whatever so we
have a few high quality Frozen samples
of these extinct animals and if
something was frozen if an animal was
frozen let's say 30,000 years ago you
should be able
to all it organs all its fluids body
fluids blood Etc will be frozen
perfectly well it should be not that
difficult to extract high quality DNA
samples from it so let's say now you
have your DNA sample
okay woly Mammoth or cave lion or
whatever now that you have the DNA all
you have to do is to use a technique
similar to cloning in cloning what you
do is well I'm not go into the technical
details but you take out the DNA and
insert it into into uh into an
unfertilized egg and uh you do something
that makes the egg start dividing that's
the long and the short of it very I mean
not giving you a technical explanation
but that's how it's done how Dolly the
sheep was clone and how cloning is
generally done very similar kind of
thing you do to make this happen so once
you have the DNA which is in good
condition then you all you do is
essentially you take an egg from an
let's say for a wly
mammoth to bring a wly mammoth back back
to
life um you take an an animal that's
very similar which is let's say the
elephant and you implant the DNA in in
the elephant and you induce the egg cell
the single Exel to start multiplying and
that's how you get it done that's one of
the techniques that you can use so it's
definitely possible if you have a cave
lion whose DNA you are able to extract
then you would want to to use a regular
Lion's egg cell most
likely yeah a regular lion so you take
you see you you you
um you cidate youate youdate a lioness
and gently take out one of the egg cells
and then you implant the DNA into that
and then you can uh have it implanted
into lonus again after it is um it
starts dividing that sort of thing so
it's definitely possible with the kind
of uh understanding of genetics and
biotechnology that we currently have
it's certainly possible so I think it
may happen soon in the next decade you
may have wly
mammoths uh back back on planet Earth
it's possible it is certainly
possible okay rajor gon says who do you
think is the greatest polymath of all
time uh Leonardo Leonardo da Vinci comes
to mind would you agree
okay polymaths um what's a
polymath a polymath is is a person of of
EX extraordinary
knowledge very wide knowledge or
learning it's a person whose competence
who whose knowledge goes across multiple
domains very different domains very
different subjects so the person can
draw from different pools of knowledge
very different pools of knowledge and
apply them either either individually or
in a
multi-disciplinary fashion to to find
new insights or solve problems and so on
that's essentially what um a polymath is
and Leonardo the wici is is said to be a
classic example of a polymath now who's
the greatest polymath I don't know but
let me give you some examples of
polymaths okay
uh let's let's first think about people
who have a high degree of competence in
let's say more than
one
field so let's go to Google and let me
put some some obscure some non obscure
individuals one is Jon Snow now it's not
the character from Game of Thrones I'm
talking about John know the
cricketer this guy was a fast bowler who
played for for England so he was a high
quality fast bowler very nasty guy he
once ran into s gasar okay very um
good fast bowler but after he retired he
became a poet and he published two
volumes of volumes of poetry so that's
not exactly a polymath but it's
definitely a person with interesting
competences in different places in
different fields now there is Brian
May Brian May is the lead guitarist of
Queen right with Freddy Mercury but he's
also an
astrophysicist he's Dr Brian May so a
musician and astrophysicist that's kind
of interesting that's two very different
fields then there is Eric uh I
Kona one of the great
footballers okay Manchester United one
of the greats and also an actor a pretty
good actor so once again two Fields then
there is Alex Alexander
kelin the greatest wrestler of all time
absolute Beast of a man he only lost two
matches and won I don't know more than
800 he lost his first match and his last
match so one of the great not one of the
greats the alltime great of wrestling
he's also a politician okay so that's
interesting then I can give you some
other names Brahma
Gupta so he was a polymath he Brahma
Gupta was a mathematician an astronomer
who was a physicist who gave the theory
of gwak kran which is uh gravity right
so there is brahmagupta then there is
bascar aara
bascara uh so he was as you can see
they're saying he's a polymath polymath
mathematician astronomer engineer so I
can give you a couple of Indian examples
then how about Leonard
Oiler okay Leonard Oiler a Swiss
polymath mathematician physicist
astronomer logician geographer
engineer uh I'm sure you've all heard of
Nicola
Tesla great great man one of the great
inventors he was an engineer futurist
inventor and all uh John Fon noyman John
Fon
noyman another absolute genius was a
mathematician physicist computer
scientist and
engineer now who else could I give you I
could give you Fred Hy one of my
favorites Fred hoy so he was a
cosmologist he was an astronomer but he
was
also he was also so he he is the guy who
coined the term Big Bang okay Fred Hy
but he also wrote science fiction novels
uh I've read two of his science fiction
novels a for Andromeda and the black
cloud I'm sure there's more he wrote
short stories radio plays he co-created
television serials and so on so there's
Fred Hil who's definitely a polymath and
I would add the name of subash
kak subash kak is a computer
scientist he uh has done work in
mathematics he is currently doing
research in physics and he is also a
historian so bashak is is an example of
a polymath so that's what polymaths are
now who's the greatest of them all I
don't know maybe Leon Leon the wici
maybe there maybe may have been some
others but yeah I just give you a whole
bunch of names and if you find this
interesting do feel free to do your own
further research in
this okay so there is that now let's go
to the next question gorov
jat uh M says why are room temperature
superconductors a big deal is it a big
thing what problems does room
temperature super
conductivity actually solve and what are
the complexities in making a room
temperature
superconductor so what's a
superconductor h a superconductor or a
super conducting material is something
that allows electricity to flow with
zero resistance which means that no
energy is lost in the form of heat
during
transmission if you take copper wires
they're an excellent conductor of
electricity but there is some loss maybe
10 15% L maybe 5% 10% loss see right now
we have an electrical grid and all this
current U everywhere around the world
more more or less it it goes through
copper wires of various kinds and you
typically lose 5 to 10% of the
electricity that that's generated during
Transmission in the form of heat because
of the inherent resistance of the copper
of of copper as a material everything
has some
resistance now super a superc conducting
material is a material that has zero
resistance so you don't lose anything I
but the problem is that you can't do
that at room temperature okay so that's
why room temperature superc conductivity
is is one of the one of the so-called
holy Grails in physics and Material
Science right so essentially if you have
that then you can have electricity being
you can transmit electricity without
losing any of it in the form of heat
okay so if you have room room
temperature super conductivity then
power distribution would be way more
efficient and way more
economical now it's not just about power
transmission there there's there's many
other technologies that you could U that
could be transformed if you have room
temperature superconductors for example
MRI machines you know today's MRI
machines they need liquid helium for
cooling so if you don't need that
cooling anymore it'll become way more
powerful and way more efficient way
cheaper MRI machines then you can have
magnetically liated trains that are
cheaper much cheaper to
operate uh more powerful and more
compact electric motors electric motors
and
generators you know these days Quantum
Computing has become a big thing have
you seen the quantum computers with this
this giant gigantic
apparatus much of it is the cooling
mechanism so if you don't need complex
cooling systems anymore because of
superc conductivity then it will be a
revolutionary step forward in Quantum
comp computers Quantum
Computing and so on so forth I can give
you so many other examples so
um but the deal is that superc
conductivity doesn't work at room
temperature it's been it's it's
extremely difficult to have superc
conductors work at room room temperature
and and why is why why is why is it so
to understand why it's so you to
understand how superc conductivity works
so to give you a very brief overview
superc conductivity relies on pairs of
electrons called Cooper pairs moving
together in a material in a coordinated
way now if the material has a certain
temperature higher temperature then
thermal vibrations in the material will
break up the Cooper Pairs and that then
you will have no then you won't have
superc conductivity so to get a material
to maintain this delicate Quantum State
you need to cool it
significantly significantly below room
temperature and
to have this phenomenon happen at room
temperature you need extremely precisely
engineered Crystal structures and
electron
behaviors so that's the challenge so
right now currently the challenge that
we Face the challenges that we face
towards superconductivity
is that most materials that are
promising
superconductor uh candidates they are
unstable
at room temperature or or they degrade
very rapidly and and some so-called room
temperature superconductors only work
under extreme pressures so it's room
temperature but it's under tremendous
pressure and uh it's very difficult to
uh to to you need a material at a
certain amount of Purity extremely high
level of Purity and a very specific kind
of Crystal fracture and to manufacture
that is extremely challenging
and many so-called high temperature
superconductors they can only carry
small amounts of current before losing
their superconducting properties so
these are the challenges that we are
facing and that's why you don't have
room room temperature superconductors
recently there was this this claim of
this this exotic material right called
lk99 or something it generated a lot of
attention but eventually it was not it
we could not verify it as a genuine room
room temperature
superconductor uh so so that these are
the challenges but if we can crack the
problem and we can have a
genuinely successful room temperature
superconductor it would completely
revolutionize so many different fields
so that's super conductivity and you may
have heard of semiconductors right I
mean in phones and computers everywhere
we use semiconductors semiconductors are
dual use kind of materials uh in the
absence of an electrical current they
don't
conduct uh they don't conduct
electricity but if you if you apply a
current or voltage or something they
will conduct electricity so they can act
act as Gates and that's why you have the
and Gates or Gates nor Gates and so on
so forth in in transistors and uh semic
conector semicon conductor chips anyhow
so that's a deal with room temperature
superconductors
Rajan says with so much adulteration and
the general quality of farm produce
going down are supplements necessary to
maintain a healthy body um you know what
if you're talking about India the
quality of farm produce is still way
Superior to that of the US in the US if
you look at pictures of people from the
1950s 60s Etc people were very fit there
was hardly any obesity there and today
everyone's obese or or significant
population percentage of the population
the US is obese something is gone wrong
with the food supply Everything is
overprocessed Everything has
contaminants everything has adulteration
and overall it makes people sick the
same people who live in the US they go
to Europe for a month they lose a lot of
weight so the US has terrible food
quality
terrible in India it's not the case I am
sure there are issues in India as well
but it's not the scale that the US has
so if you want to uh maintain a healthy
body I would suggest that eat what
people used to eat a thousand years ago
if it wasn't available a thousand years
ago don't eat it very simple answer very
simple rule of thumb okay if it wasn't
available a th years ago don't eat it uh
so eat Whole Foods eat unprocessed Foods
don't eat junk food very easy to say but
difficult to practice in real life and
so on that's one thing you can do uh and
supplements there's no harm taking
supplements a multivitamin why not it's
like an insurance policy at best you
will pee it out at best at worst and at
best it it'll help you in some way so uh
supplements I I have nothing against
them you can take them don't over overdo
it don't take a supplement for
everything but a general multiv vitamin
is is I would say it's essentially
harmless and maybe it'll do do some
good
yep tun Kumar RI says how to give a
solid comeback in life I have no job I
wasted four years in upsc preparation
without reading much I am 25 years old
I'm your blind follower and diard fan
from the past three years your one word
will change my life first of all don't
please I would say don't follow anyone
blindly okay and I really appreciate
what you're saying here and I I
genuinely appreciate it but please don't
follow anybody blindly uh now how to
make a comeback you're 25 years old
you've wasted four years upsc
preparation did not read much so first
of all I would say do not start
considering yourself a failure
every successful person has failed
multiple times multiple multiple times a
failure is is a way of finding out what
doesn't work for you okay so don't start
considering yourself a failure that's
the first thing I would say secondly you
have to acknowledge and accept and
own what's happened you cannot say you
cannot make excuses that it happened for
so and so reason or whatever and you
can't blame others you have to own own
what happened so you are owning it over
here you are saying that I wasted four
years in upsc preparation did not read
much and I have no job and so on so you
you you know what the situation is and
you're owning up to it right now you
that so you have you acknowledge you
accept your own then you need to analyze
what went wrong the mechanics and
dynamics of how it went wrong and why it
went wrong and the objective is not to
uh do self-criticism all that it's the
objective is to ensure that it doesn't
happen again so you saying that you
wasted four years in upsc preparation
but you did not read much
why is that so you to ask yourself was
it because you knew that it's not the
right path for you but maybe somebody
was forcing you to take it or maybe
there was peer pressure or family
pressure or some other pressure I I
don't know right so you have to find out
what what is the cause of this
particular phase of life in which you
could not achieve what you were
apparently trying to achieve the upsc
thing right so you have to
analyze and and figure out what went
wrong why did this happen how did it
happen and learn the lesson from that to
ensure that this sort of thing doesn't
happen then once you have that you need
to Define clear
goals you need to have a set of goals
goals that are written down written
down and measurable goals not I'll get
better but it has to be measurable and
quantifiable in some way it has to be
written down it has to be quantifiable
measurable and it has to be time bound
so your goal you have to divide into
three
categories your short term goal your
medium-term long and your long-term goal
your long-term goal can be something you
want to achieve in 10 or 20 years your
medium-term goal is something you want
to achieve in three years and short-term
goal is something you want to achieve in
the next three months so you have a big
long-term goal and you break it down
into small pieces and one threeyear
piece the first piece is your
medium-term goal and how will you
achieve the medium-term goal is by
chunking it into even smaller pieces and
the first chunk is your thre Monon goal
which is your short-term goal so that's
how you plan and schedule your
comeback then you have to develop a plan
of action so you break down your goals
into smaller manageable steps with
timelines and strategies to execute them
and then what is the strategy to execute
this because you know it's okay to have
plans and dreams and hopes but how do
you make it happen how do you
execute you execute by changing your
behavior you don't try change your
mindset okay never try and change your
mindset change your behavior what is
behavior it's habits it's rituals it's
priorities priorities in mindset but
habits and
rituals habit is a ritual you know that
so you need to audit your habits what
are what are my current habits when I
wake up what do I do so and so time of
the day what what do I typically do and
so on you to audit your habits and you
have to change your behaviors change
your behavior by creating new habits or
new
rituals okay that's what you have to do
it's very important to take action in
that manner and then you have to cut out
all negativity by and that's how you set
your priorities in life you have to seek
positivity you have to cut out the
people who bring negativity in your life
you have to get get them away keep them
away sometimes it will happen that you
can't do anything about it maybe it's
your family maybe it's your friends and
you just do anything about it then what
you do is you limit your your
communication or contact with them and
you seek positivity
by by making a list of
mentors maybe you'll never meet those
mentors in your life but there are
people who admire and you either read
their books by that you get the
positivity positivity and and path
forward in your life or you watch
YouTube videos or something of those
people or whatever something you to find
a solution you to find a way okay to
bring positivity into your
life so by doing this you take small
steps you move you execute you take
action and the attitude is that you have
to keep executing you to keep moving you
have to make things happen it'll start
in a very slow manner but you have to
keep it going keep it going build the
momentum and you have to become a high
agency person a high agency person is a
person who will make things happen if I
want something I'll find a way to do it
I'll find a way to to achieve that there
are people who dreams and hopes but they
never move they just sit where they are
and they keep dreaming that's a low
agency person a high agency person is
once they have an objective they will
stop at nothing to make it happen anyhow
they'll get it done so you have to
become that sort of
person and then you have to keep on
reassessing where you are on a daily
basis on a weekly basis so you need to
have scheduled meetings with yourself
every day or every week or whatever okay
so and so day in time I'm going to sit
down and I'm going to have a meeting
with myself
okay what was the plan
what was achieved what was not achieved
what went wrong what went right and so
on so forth okay and you have to have
that habit and uh you need to have
patience because life is not a Sprint
life is a
marathon so that's how we make a
comeback in life and you have to eat
healthy you to sleep well and you have
to get fit and strong that really really
helps eat healthy sleep well and get fit
get strong that's how you make a
comeback in life everybody goes through
bad phases in life there's not a single
successful person who has not failed
multiple times so don't let them let
that U overwhel overwhelm you what
matters is what you what you do next and
that's how you do it so all the best my
friend all the best I wish you
success gorov says how to be disciplined
and hardworking especially when you're
the laziest
guy so what is laziness laziness is is a
behavior it's a habit right so
um so replace that habit or that
behavior with a different
Behavior imagine this okay this just a
hypothetical thought experiment imagine
that you have 5 hours left to live five
hours of life
left what will you do will it still
still just relax and sit by or will you
get something done I want to do
something in the last five hours of my
life maybe you want to meet some people
maybe have things You' have not said to
people or maybe to set some things in
order or whatever you'll immediately
take action the next 5 hours right where
what happened to the laziness it
evaporated instantaneously didn't it so
laziness I mean everybody wants to be
lazy I would love to be lazy I would
love to spend three days on on a on a
mountain side or on a beach but I don't
allow that to happen I mean you can
schedule that once in a while but you
have to work hard so laziness is a habit
you have to replace that with a
different habit look it's like this
all you have to do is to pretend like
you're an actor an actor and you have to
wear different hats in life so you can
say that okay if I wear this hat I will
behave in this manner now I take this
hat off and I put this hat on then I'll
behave in a different manner you have to
have personas and roles as an actor so
let's say in a day you typically need to
do three different kinds of things but
you're too lazy so you tell yourself
okay at so and so time I'm going to put
this hat on and when I put that hat on
for two hours then for two hours I'm
going to pretend like I am a certain
kind of persona and I'll act in in a
certain way and do do certain things and
once you get into into the process of
doing that over and over again it
becomes easier so laziness is just a
habit hard working hard is also a habit
uh all you have to do is that you tell
yourself I'm an actor I'll put on a hat
and I'll do certain amount of certain
kind of work for a certain amount of
time uh it's all about changing your
behavior and changing your behavior
through action changes your mindset so
that's how we do
it okay Mah mahish rra says Is it
feasible for a politician or a leader to
express genuine honesty in their
speech have you heard of the term
political
correctness political correctness
everybody has heard this term have you
heard heard a term called leader
leadership correctness or something no
it's only political correctness
political correctness is nothing but a
form of lying isn't it you don't say
what you really feel or think or mean
you say something that's acceptable to
all and offensive to none that is
nothing but lying politicians have to
lie why do politicians have to lie lie
because they need votes they
can't afford to offend people they have
to try and Pander to as many people as
possible so politicians cannot be
entirely honest in their speech I I
cannot think of a single politician who
can afford to be honest entirely honest
when they
speak now cons contrast that with a king
or an
emperor if you have a king or an emperor
does the king or an emperor need to be
dishonest or can they afford to be
honest they can of course they can
because they don't need to depend on
votes every five years or four years
right they they hold the Reigns of power
they know what power is and they know
how to wield it and that's why they
don't need anyone's
votes so that's the difference between a
politician and a genuine leader or or or
a dictator that's the difference between
a politician and a dictator a king is a
dictator an emperor is a dictator now
what's a leader a leader
a politician can be a leader but and a
king can also be a leader but a leader
is a person I'll tell you what a leader
is and how it is different from a
politician a leader is a person who
needs to take
the to to take to make choices that are
unpopular a leader is a person who has
to be able to make unpopular choices
because popular choices are the lazy
stupid choices that everybody loves but
it doesn't take the country forward
it's the unpopular difficult choices
that are painful in the short term that
will actually take the country forward
and that only a genuine leader can do
that a politician can't do
that so that's the difference between a
politician and a leader a politician
cannot ever be completely 100% genuinely
honest in their
speech a leader a genuine leader has no
choice but to do that big
difference okay let's take some
questions I still have more questions
but I'll take some questions from the
live chat for the next 10 minutes
so I've already covered the
kumb uh okay this is an interesting
question by anit by Anita Anita what do
you think of the Indian reporting of the
kumbam my opinion is that they focused
too much on foreigners instead of
regular people from all parts of India
they saved for years for this event okay
I have not really been following the
Indian coverage of the Kumba what I have
seen what little I have seen is that yes
Indian the Indian media IND are focusing
on foreigners and they they're focusing
on some celebrity people and they're
focusing on a guy who was is a former
IIT guy and who is now um sasi and that
sort of thing they're focusing on a few
selected people and they're not they're
not focusing on on the on the big
picture the Indian media I I find it
very disappointing very very low quality
low standards media they they all all
they want is sensation to sens
sensationalize everything which means
they'll try and find something that's
either controversial or something
Sensational like a foreigners come to
India to participate in a Hindu festival
wow let's let's focus on that the next
48 hours that sort of thing it's it's
sad it's unfortunate our our media is is
very shallow most of it not all of it
most of it most of it is tremendously
shallow and utterly
useless um like I say like I keep saying
please keep raising your standards the
media hasn't done that so yeah that's
what we have and it's unfortunate uh we
should like you saying Anita that we
should focus on the millions of Indians
the ordinary people who have saved for
years to be able to travel all the way
there and participate in this event
that's what we should be focusing on we
should be focusing on the significance
of the event on on and and and on on the
people who are making it what it is but
now we're going to focus on whatever is
Sensational and to a large extent the
media does this because the Indian
Indian average Indian viewer wants
sensationalism and everything it's just
a sad
mindset that we have in India very low
standards mindset it's going to be a
long time and before we we change in
in get better as a nation and and a and
a civilization and
society fishball says uh can you please
bless me I have a g exam on the 23rd
January I now don't be able to give my
100% John attempt I promise I'll give my
100% on the April attempt okay I wish
you all the best I give you my blessings
go for the Jan attempt at least it's
going to be an experience it will give
you a taste of how the exam is done and
then you can give your absolute 100% in
the April attempt so go for it all the
best and do
well
okay geopolitical du says why is Iran
relocating its capital toan from to
makran from thean makran is are they
doing it really I I haven't heard of
this let me see let us go to Google um
Iran capital relocation really uh
relocation are they doing it Iran makes
Iran eyes marran in the southern coast
as its new capital after whatever so
they're considering moving their capital
from thean
to wherever so I'm not going to open
these articles and try and read what
their opinion is because I don't know I
don't care what their opinion is if they
are trying to do this what could be the
reason so for that let me try and look
at the map I have not even heard this
news I'm not aware of it let me look at
the map where is makran it's obviously
in the southern coast the makran
coast So Tan is All the Way North over
here um it's near aeran it's near the
Caspian Sea uh now macran is all the way
down
south it's called the marran coast
marran um it went straight into the
place okay Mar here it
is chabahar
Bay so uh it would be interesting if
Iran would decide to move the capital
all the way to the pakist almost at the
Pakistan
border uh it would
be very close to the Sea I'm not sure
why they would do that I have to think
about this but interesting if it is true
interesting uh historically their
capital for a very long time has been
tan orig it was paral po but yeah uh not
sure right now I I I I'll have to think
about it and consider the
full the full ramifications and possible
reasons for
this Amisha says is dark energy a real
thing
well we're not sure look um to the best
of our understanding about 70% of the
mass energy composition of the universe
is this unknown substance that seems to
be responsible for the accelerating
expansion of the universe so as far as
we know the best understanding that we
have had thus that we have to date uh
about four to 5% of the matter of the
universe matter energy composition of
the universe is visible matter
everything we see in the in the night
night sky all the stars galaxies nebula
Pulsar quazar everything dust all of
that is about 5% everything we see is 5%
about 25% or so is dark matter
dark matter we have some understanding
of it it's some kind of uh particle or
family of particles or class of
particles it could also be explained by
modified newon Newtonian gravity M but
dark matter is definitely much more
tangible but Dark Energy we haven't the
least idea of what it is is it is it a
additional force is it is it a is it a
fifth force is it uh is it a fluid of
some kind we don't
know uh so we don't know it's it's
extremely mysterious it's something that
causes the accelerating expansion of the
universe and there's this new Theory the
Timescape Theory that's recently become
um that's come out and become well known
which says that there is no dark energy
and it's actually the differential
passage of time in different parts of
the universe that causes the
accelerating expansion of the
universe we know that U from the uh from
theory of general relativity we know
that matter affects the the the rate at
which time
passes and there are parts of the
universe that are absolute voids there's
no matter so time passes at a different
speed over there compar at a faster rate
or there compared to regions of the
universe where you have a lot of matter
like uh Dark Matter filaments and G
Galaxy Super clusters and so on so it's
because of this different rate at which
time passes that we have this expansion
of the universe and that's what the
theory says it's very interesting Theory
and it seems to solve a lot of problems
but it's early days for that so we're
not sure if dark energy is even a real
thing and that's why yeah yeah that's
that's how interesting physics is we
know we understand so little of the
universe right
now Sonia says please make a library
video tour I know I've had this request
for such a long time I really need to
stop being lazy and do it so thank you
for the reminder Sonia
G okay um
okay Lost Child says why is India silent
on the us acquiring Greenland and is the
US going to build a military base there
they already
have P2 space Force Base what is P2 now
let me Google that I am not aware of
what p
is so let us go to Google search on the
map in
P2
Greenland aha interesting
our friend The Lost Child is given is G
is giving us interesting
information ah T So this seems to be
some kind of military in oh look at that
they have a gigantic Runway let's
measure the distance how long is this
Runway ah 3 kilometers that is it can
take any kind of aircraft including
strategic bombers and so on so this
seems to be us base in the region in in
the Greenland region and why would the
have a base here they own Denmark
essentially they own Western Europe so
they'll have it and now they want to
take it over entirely so look if they
want to do it there's nobody that can
stop them my question is this
okay who is India to criticize the
US is India the the an equal of the
US the top three nations in terms of
hard power are are the US Russia and
China India is number four
now the US is a hard hard power score
about of of of about 94 India is
4.9 I mean they are more than 20 times
more powerful than you who are you to
criticize them and what what purpose
does it serve for a mosquito to
criticize an annoy an elephant what
purpose will it solve will it serve do
we get something out of
it okay so
it's not our business if the US wants to
take over everybody let them do it just
pray and hope it it doesn't they don't
want to come and take us over that's all
we have to hide our capabilities and
bide our time so yeah that's why we not
doing it we will not do it we will we'll
stay very silent about this okay we
don't criticize the big boss we don't do
it all right two hours 15 minutes plus
as always I'm going to end it over here
so thank you so much everybody very
interesting questions you've asked and
uh next week I'll take as many more as
possible of your
questions and uh yes Mr 8ers coming very
soon coming very soon all right thank
you very much everybody take care keep
raising your standards and keep asking
questions and I'll see you next week
thank care take care bye-bye